Good day, today's דף *daf* is פ״ו *peh vav* 86, we are
a little behind, we took up on פ״ה עמוד ב׳ *peh hey
amud bet*, it goes like this, let's just start very quickly from
the first wide line, middle of the first wide line. ריש לקיש
הוה מציין מערתא דרבנן *Resh Lakish havei mtzayen me'arta d'rabbanan*, ריש לקיש
*Resh Lakish* was marking the caves of the רבנן Rabbis *Rabbanan*, so
people would know to avoid them, or I don't know, maybe it
indicates an early sort of practice to go and pray by them.
כי מטא למערתא דרבי חייא Chiya, *ki mata l'me'arta d'Rabbi Chiya*, when
he came to the cave of רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya. *Rabbi Chiya*,
איעלמא מיניה *i'alma minei*, it was hidden from him, like he was
right there but he couldn't find it. חלש דעתיה *chalash dateih*, he
became despondent. אמר Amar, *amar*, he said, רבונו של עולם Ribbono shel
olam, *Ribbono Shel Olam*, לא פלפלתי תורה Torah כמותו *lo pilpalti Torah
kamoto*? Did I not, was I not as, you know, as analytical,
like פלפול *pilpul*, right? Just like sort of the analytical sharpness, the,
you know, sort of of learning תורה Torah *Torah*. Was I not
sort
of as great of a תורה Torah *Torah* prowess as he was?
And you of course remember the whole story with רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan. *Rabbi Yochanan* that ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* would cut him down
and רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* asked questions. So didn't I
have as great תורה Torah *Torah* prowess? יצת בת קול ואמרה *yatzat
bat kol v'amrah*, a heavenly voice came out and said, תורה Torah
כמותו פלפלת *Torah kamoto pilpalta*. Yes, you know, in your ability to
analyze and understand and what, you know, you know תורה *Torah*, that
you were as great as him. תורה כמותו לא רבצת *Torah kamoto
lo ravatzta*, but you have not spread תורה *Torah* like he did.
So that gets back also to the lesson of like the מעשים
טובים Ma'asim Tovim, *ma'asim tovim*, right? How much did that help other
people? I mean it helped רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*, but
how, you know, much did that spread תורה *Torah* throughout כלל ישראל
Klal Yisrael, *Klall Yisrael*? Now we're going to see a story about
how רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya. *Rabbi Chiya* spread תורה *Torah* through כלל
ישראל Klal Yisrael. *Klall Yisrael*. כי הוו מינצו רבי חנינא Rebbi Chanina
ורבי חייא Chiya. *ki havu mintzu Rabbi Chanina v'Rabbi Chiya*, when רבי
חנינא Rebbi Chanina. *Rabbi Chanina* and רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya *Rabbi Chiya*
would argue, אמר ליה Amar lei, רבי חנינא Rebbi Chanina. לרבי חייא
*amar lei Rabbi Chanina l'Rabbi Chiya*, רבי חנינא Rebbi Chanina *Rabbi Chanina*
would say to רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya, *Rabbi Chiya*, בהדי דידי מנצית
*bahadi didi menatzat*? You see, you think you can argue with me?
חס ושלום אי משתכחת תורה מישראל *chas v'shalom ei mishtakchat Torah m'Yisrael*,
God forbid if תורה *Torah* was ever forgotten from the Jewish people,
מהדרינא לה מפלפולי *mehadreina lah mipilpuli*. There's the word פלפול *pilpul* again.
I would be able to restore it with my great analytical ability,
right? So I would be able to sort of derive everything from
first principles or something like that. Somehow even if it was all
forgotten, I would be able to recover it. אמר ליה Amar lei,
רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya? לרבי חנינא *amar lei Rabbi Chiya l'Rabbi Chanina*,
so רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya, *Rabbi Chiya* said back to רבי חנינא
Rebbi Chanina *Rabbi Chanina*, בהדי דידי מנצית *bahadi didi menatzat*? You think
you're going to argue with me? דאבדי לתורה דלא תשתכח מישראל *d'avdi
l'Torah d'lo tishtakach m'Yisrael*. I would make sure it never got forgotten.
You, יישר כוח Shkoach. *yasher koach*, you would restore it. I, I
have already acted in a way to ensure that it won't be
forgotten. Why, what did you do? מאי עבדנא *mai avadna*, what do,
you know, what did I do? אזלינא ושדינא כיתנא וגדלינא נישבי *azlina
v'shadina kitna v'gadlina nishbei*. I went and I planted flaxseeds and I
grew, what do you call it? I grew a net. I grew
flax and I made out of them nets. וציידנא טבי *v'tzaidna tavi*,
and I captured with a net deer. ומאכילנא בשרייהו ליתמי *umachilna bisrayhu
l'yatmei*. I slaughtered the deer and I fed orphans their meat, so
it was all going for לשם שמים Shamayim? *l'shem shamayim*, every part
of the process. ואריכנא מגילתא *v'arichna megilta*,
and I basically prepared, you know, scrolls from the hides of the
deer. וכתבנא חמישה חומשי *v'katavna chamisha chumshei*,
and I wrote, you know, five, the five books of the תורה
*Torah*, each one on a separate scroll. וסליקנא למתא *v'salikna l'mata*, and
I went to a city. ומקרינא חמישה ינוקי בחמישה חומשי *umakrina chamisha
yenukei b'chamisha chumshei*, and I taught, I tucked together five children and
I taught each one of them a separate one of the scrolls,
one בראשית *Bereishit*, one שמות *Shemot*, one whatever, okay, חמישה בחמישה חומשי
*chamisha b'chamisha chumshei*. ומתנינא שישה ינוקי שישה סדרי *umathnina shisha yenukei shisha
sidrei*.
And then I took six children and I taught each one of
them one of the orders of משניות Mishnayot, *Mishnayot*. Of course it
doesn't say he wrote it because it was the orders of the
משניות *Mishnayot* were בעל פה *b'al peh*. Okay, so I did, you
know, I had each one own a piece of it. ואמינא להו
*v'amina lehu*,
and I said to them, עד דאדדרא ואתא *ad d'dadra v'ata*,
I'm going to leave now. Before I come back the next time,
what I want you to do while I'm gone, you know, I'll
be back in a year, is אקרו אהדדי *akru ahadadi*,
teach each other your piece, so read the תורה *Torah*. You, the
kid who knows בראשית *Bereishit*, I want you while I'm gone to
teach all your friends בראשית *Bereishit*. And you, the kid who knows
שמות *Shemot*, teach all your friends שמות *Shemot*. You, the guy who
knows זרעים *Zeraim*, I want you to teach everybody זרעים *Zeraim*. Okay?
אקרו אהדדי ואתנו אהדדי *akru ahadadi v'atnu ahadadi*, teach each other the
משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*. And therefore דאבדי לה לתורה דלא תשתכח מישראל *d'avdi
lah l'Torah d'lo tishtakach m'Yisrael*, I made it so that תורה *Torah*
shall not be forgotten from Israel. So of course this is a
very beautiful story. First of all from a modern perspective, the whole
idea of, you know, where they talk about about sustainable, you know,
what's the phrase? I, you know, yeah, sustainable, you know, I think,
yeah,
creating a sustainable system. So it's not just like, oh, I went
and I taught in a million different places. But I think the
very fact that it gets us back to the planting of the
nets, right, it's not just like I donated some money and we
bought it. Like it's almost like I set up a whole system
that could be self-sustained.
Okay, but more also the sort of the pedagogical prowess, right? You're
teaching kids. You're not teaching adults where you get to show off
how brilliant you are and how many, you know, brilliant conceptual distinctions
you're doing. A very basic teacher of basic text, which is about
memorizing, right? It's משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* and חומש *Chumash*. It's not about
analysis at all. It's about knowledge, right? So you're sort of but
understanding that it's not about how brilliant you are. It's about doing
the hard work that's required, you know, for the sake of כלל
ישראל. And and גוף פלפ. Guf Pelp.
Right. They just they used the word גוף פלפ Guf Pelp all
the time and now he's
it's the opposite of גוף פלפ, Guf Pelp, exactly that, exactly that.
And also the pedagogical point, the way the מהרש"א Maharsha says it,
right, is that he made every child into a לומד Lomeid and
a מלמד. Melameid. He made every child into a learner and a
teacher, right, and that power that you teach others and you're, you
know, and the collaborative nature of it, also the fact that each
one owned the section, so you can feel a sense of ownership
over your piece, right, and then what that does to sort of
empower people and to make them, you know, part of the process
and not just receivers but also givers, right, there's so powerful here
and it's exactly the point that you, you know, you're patting yourself
on the back, look what a huge תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham I
am and I could restore, which almost you almost hear a subtext
of רבי חנינא Rebbi Chanina, like, I wish תורה would be forgotten
and I could show everybody how I could like restore it, how
great I am, right, whereas it's like, you know what, it isn't
about you and it isn't about how smart you are and it
isn't about whatever, you know, the point is about what are you
doing, you know, for כלל ישראל, so you got to do here
to protect it that the תורה never does get forgotten.
Let me just say this in a self-serving context, but we shouldn't
argue.
Yeah, that's true, okay, and you also wonder what the גמרא Gemara
means when they used to argue, like how many times can you
have the same exchange? But anyway, but it's a very sort of
powerful מוסר Mussar here, right, about like what really matters and also
about the like educational, sort of pedagogic principles here. Okay, so now
it says like this, והיינו דאמר רבי, V'hainu d'amar Rebbi, that's what
רבי Rebbi means when he said גדולי מעשי חייא, Gedoli Ma'aseh Chiya,
great are the deeds of חייא, maybe echoing the part before about
תורה versus מעשים טובים, Ma'asim Tovim, remember that part before whether you
were great in מעשים טובים, the deeds of חייא. It's not just,
you know what, it doesn't really matter how brilliant of a תלמיד
חכם Talmid Chacham you were, these deeds were what were the most
powerful. Okay, גדולי מעשי חייא. Gedoli Ma'aseh Chiya. אמר
ליה רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, Amar lei Rebbi Yishmael b'Rebbi Yosi, אפילו
ממר? Afilu mimar? So רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rebbi Yishmael b'Rebbi Yosi
said to him, was he even greater than you? Than רבי? Rebbi?
Than you know, you רבי יהודה הנשיא? Rebbi Yehuda Hanasi? אמר ליה
אין, Amar lei in, yes. אפילו מאבא, Afilu me'abba, was he even
greater than your father? אמר ליה חס ושלום לא תהא כזאת בישראל,
Amar lei Chas v'Shalom lo tehei kazos b'Yisrael, God forbid, no, that
would never be such a thing. Of course the irony being that
my father, oh,
meaning
my father, אפילו מאבא, Afilu me'abba, my father's
father, אבא Abba is רבי ישמעאל's
Rebbi Yishmael father, רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosi, that is.
Oh, really? Huh. That's what it says there. Hmm, I guess because
he wouldn't refer to רבי's Rebbi father as אבא. Abba. Okay, that's
interesting. Okay, יישר כוח.
Fine. Let me just check רש"י. Rashi. I mean, I guess they're
not diverging from רש"י. Rashi. I don't know why I thought it
meant otherwise. Okay, interesting. All right, moving on.
Okay, חס ושלום לא תהא כזאת בישראל. Chas v'Shalom lo tehei kazos
b'Yisrael. If it was רבי's Rebbi father, it would have been interesting
because רבי's Rebbi father was the one who said that who said
that he himself was like, you know, who he showed the ענוה
Anavah that he himself was a, you know, חומץ בן יין, Chometz
ben Yayin, he called רבי Rebbi etc. But anyway, but I hear
the read that it's his father. Okay, moving on.
אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rebbi Zeira, so asserted רבי זירא. Rebbi Zeira.
אמש חזי לי רבי יוסי בר חנינא, Emesh chezi li Rebbi Yosi
bar Chanina, last night appeared to me רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi the
son of רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina, אמרתי לו, Amarti lo, and presumably
in a dream, I said to him, אצל מי אתה תקוע, Eitzel
mi ata takua, by who are you planted, like who, you know,
where do you dwell up there in עולם הבא, Olam Haba, who's
your חברותא? Chavrusa? אמר לי אצל רבי יוחנן, Amar li eitzel Rebbi
Yochanan, by רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan, ורבי יוחנן אצל מי, V'Rebbi Yochanan
eitzel mi, and who's רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan sort of next to?
אצל רבי ינאי. Eitzel Rebbi Yannai. ורבי ינאי אצל מי, V'Rebbi Yannai
eitzel mi, so this is the hierarchy in heaven, okay? אצל רבי
חנינא, Eitzel Rebbi Chanina, by רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina Remember that was
the רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina who just argued with רבי חייא. Rabbi
Chiya ורבי חנינא אצל מי, V'Rebbi Chanina eitzel mi, and who's רבי
Rebbe, חנינא by? אצל רבי חייא, Eitzel Rebbi Chiya, by רבי חייא.
Rabbi Chiya So there again you see רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya, had
the higher position in גן עדן. Gan Eden. אמרתי לו ורבי יוחנן
אצל רבי חייא לא, Amarti lo v'Rebbi Yochanan eitzel Rebbi Chiya lo,
I said to him, רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan by רבי חייא, Rabbi
Chiya. no? I don't get it. רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan why wouldn't
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan get to be right next to רבי חייא?
Rabbi Chiya, So now we're sort of implicitly comparing רבי Rebbe יוחנן
and רבי Rebbe חנינא, right? You know, so anyway, so why is
רבי Rebbe, יוחנן one, you know, not directly there to רבי חייא,
Rabbi Chiya wasn't he great?
אמר לי, Amar li, he said to me, באתר דזיקיקין דנורה ובעורין
דאשא, ba'atar d'zikikin d'nura u've'urin d'esha,
in a place where there is like fire is burning and there
are flashes of, you know, of flames, right,
shooting out, מאן מעייל בר נפחא לתמן, man ma'ayei bar nafcha letaman,
how can you bring the the
the son of the of the smelter there? Like, so you know,
the
מהרש"א Maharsha says that the בר נפחא, Bar Nafcha, that's the guy
who would actually like fan the flames, the bellows. So you don't
want to be there if the fire is raging, you're going to
get caught up. But apparently also רבי Rebbe יוחנן was called בר
נפחא, Bar Nafcha, that was his father's name or maybe that was
his profession or something. So, but it basically means like I presumably
what it means is is that there's so much heat being generated
by the two of them as we saw before from the story
that like, you know, you don't want to like, you got to
give them some space or something, which doesn't mean that his level
wasn't appropriate for that, but somehow the two of them, you know,
you had
to. אמר רבי חביבא, Amar Rabbi Chaviva, so רבי חביבא Rabbi Chaviva
said, איקלע ליה רבי חביבא בר סורמטי, ichala lei Rabbi Chaviva bar
Surmti, so
there was another רבי חביבא, Rabbi Chaviva, this רבי חביבא Rabbi Chaviva
of סורמטי, Surmti, the
son of סורמטי Surmti said to me, חזי ליה לאחד מרבנן דהוה
שכיח אליהו גביה, chazei lei le'achad me'rabbanan de'hava shechiach Eliyahu gabei, I
saw one of the רבנן Rabbis that had regular visitations from אליהו
הנביא, Eliyahu HaNavi, okay presumably
you didn't need to be a huge named רב. Rabbi. Yeah, exactly.
Okay, דבצפרא de'betzafra
and I saw this student, I knew he would regularly have some
visits from אליהו, Eliyahu, and one morning הוו שפירן עיניה, hava shapiran
einai, I saw the eyes were nice and in good condition, ואורתא
ve'orsan then by the evening דמיין כמיקליין בנורא, damyan k'nimiklin benura,
there is that fire imagery, they looked like they had been burned
by fire. אמר amar, ליה, I said to him, מאי האי, mai
hai, what happened? ואמר לי, Ve'amar li, he said to me, דאמרי
ליה לאליהו de'amri lei le'Eliyahu because I was when I was talking
to אליהו Eliyahu there, I said to him, אחוי לי רבנן כי
סלקי למתיבתא דרקיעא, achvei lei rabbanan ki salkei le'mesivta de'rakiya,
show me the רבנן Rabbis when they go up to the heavenly
academy, the heavenly בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, right because that's sort of
we've shifted now, we've shifted and we've introduced the theme of fire,
right the fire between רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya and רבי Rebbe חנינא,
and this friend says who are they dwelling by, I mean I
said who's their חברותא, chavrusah, it doesn't say exactly in the גמרא
Gemara but it's a little bit implicit, right if רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiya and רבי Rebbe חנינא are having this fire going between them.
So anyway so now we're sort of shifting, continuing with that idea
of fire, but now they're up in heaven in a ישיבה, yeshiva,
okay. So show me the רבנן as they ascend to heaven you
know in the
to the heavenly academy, כי סלקי למתיבתא דרקיעא. ki salkei le'mesivta de'rakiya.
אמר ליה, בכולהו מצי את לאסתכולי בהו, be'kulu matzei at le'istakulei le'hu,
you could look at all of them, לבר מגוהרקי דרבי חייא, lebar
mi'geharkei de'Rabbi Chiya, except for the chariot you know of רבי חייא,
Rabbi Chiya, דלא תסתכל ביה, de'lo tistaklei bei, you shouldn't look, you
shouldn't look at it while it's going up. Presumably, I don't know,
like presumably it sounds like they'd be in one place up in
heaven where they would just dwell and then every now and then
they'd go up to another place where they'd have their ישיבה. yeshiva.
Yeah they have to get to the בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, right
they have to get to the בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, so I
want to see them when they're going up to the ישיבה. yeshiva.
So don't look at the chariot of רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya מאי
סימניה, Mai simanayuh, and I said to him how will I know
that it's his chariot to not look at it? So בכולהו אזלי
מלאכי כי סלקי ונחתי, be'kulu azlei malachei ki salkei ve'nachetei, for all
of the other ones the מלאכי angels bring their chariots up and
down to the you know they get a
they get a special you know ride by the מלאכי angels up
to the heavenly chariot what?
An escort right?
Right, an escort, right, but I think it also means that they
bring up their chariot okay, לבר מגוהרקי דרבי חייא, lebar mi'geharkei de'Rabbi
Chiya, as opposed to the chariot of רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya דמנפשיה
סליק ונחית. de'minafshei salkei ve'nachetei. It goes up and down without even
any מלאכי, angels, the power of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya, himself. Okay,
so in that case, לא מצי לאוקמי אנפשיה, lo matzei le'okmei anafshei,
then he said I wasn't able to hold myself back to look
at it, like now it even gets more intriguing, right? אסתכלי ביה,
Istaklei bei, I looked at
it, אתו תרי בוטיטי דנורא, asu trei butiti de'nura, two like you
know
tongues of fire shot out, ומחיוהו לההוא גברא u'machayu le'hahu gavra
and they hit me, וסמינהו לעיניה ve'samyanu le'einai
and they blinded my eyes. למחר, Le'machar, the next day, so there
again רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya. so powerful and his chariot goes up
by itself and the fire and it blinded him. Of course there's
a whole אליהו הנביא Eliyahu HaNavi type of a thing going on
here as well.
למחר אזל ואשתטח אמערתא, Le'machar azal ve'ishtatach a'ma'arta, the next day I
went and I prostrated myself by his
cave, אמינא, amina, I said to him, מתניתא דמר מתנינא, matnisa de'mar
matnina, I learn your ברייתות, baraitas, right because רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
was like the editor of the תוספתא. Tosefta. So I am so
devoted to your teaching רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya. it's only your תוספתא,
Tosefta, you know your ברייתות baraitas that I teach, I don't teach
any of the other ברייתות. baraitas. So please like you know save
me or help me. ואיתסי Ve'itsei and I was healed. Okay, so
that's the sort of the story about רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya and
the fire and so on. Now, אליהו הוה שכיח, Eliyahu hava shechiach,
you know by the way it's also true if you think about
it because we were talking about you know I mean here's רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya. before we mentioned רבי, Rebbi we said רבי Rebbi.
wasn't as big of a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham as רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar ben Shimon, right? But these two who weren't
the biggest who aren't the biggest, excuse me, the biggest תלמידי חכמים
Talmidei Chachamim of their generation in the sense of their
intellectual prowess were still the ones to whom we owe all of
our תורה שבעל פה, Torah She'be'al Peh, right? So okay, you know
there was some, רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, how many times does anybody
remember a teaching of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון? Rabbi Elazar ben Shimon?
Right, he might have been a bigger תלמיד חכם, Talmid Chacham, right,
but because רבי Rebbi devoted himself to organizing all of this stuff
all of the material to create the משנה, Mishnah. right, that's why
we have תורה שבעל פה Torah She'be'al Peh as we have it
and רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya right, besides the story we just read,
devoted himself to organizing and creating the תוספתא, Tosefta, right? So it's
not necessarily like the stuff where you get to show off your
intellectual prowess but it's what's the best for being מרביץ תורה marbitz
Torah for כלל ישראל. Okay, so that's the story of רבי חייא.
Rabbi Chiya You know, but then it's like the story is on
such a higher level, but this guy still had like a scar
from it, you know what I mean, like his eyes were so,
right, which just shows look at the high level that they had
up in heaven, they had the high רבי Rebbi חייא had the
highest level even though this רבי Rebbi חנינא was the bigger מפלפל
בתורה. mipalpel ba'Torah. So that's exactly the story. Okay so okay אליהו
הוה שכיח במתיבתא דרבי. Eliyahu hava shechiach be'mesivta de'Rebbi. Now אליהו Eliyahu
would sometimes drop down, you know so hear that Rabbis are going
up to the ישיבה Yeshiva up in heaven. אליהו Eliyahu would sometimes
visit the ישיבה Yeshiva of רבי, Rebbi okay, down on here on
earth. יומא חד ריש ירחא הוה. Yoma chad reish yarche hove. One
day it was ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. נגה ליה Naglai and he
was postponed and he didn't come.
ולא אתא, Velo ata, he didn't come. אמר ליה מאי טעמא נגה
ליה למר, Amar lei mai ta'ama nagla lei le-mar, so רבי Rebbi
said to him, hey, you were late, what's your excuse? Okay, why
were you late today? אמר ליה אדאוקימנא לאברהם. Amar lei ad d'mokeimna
le-Avraham. Now here's what I have to do. Presumably he would only
do it on ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, okay. I wake up אברהם
Avraham up there in heaven, ומשינא ידיה Umashina yadei and I wash
his hands for him, ומצלי Umatzli and he prays. אברהם Avraham gets
up early on himself. I what can I tell you? That's a
good point. אברהם Avraham gets up early on himself, that's true. ומגנינא
ליה Umagneina lei and then I make him, I lay him down
to sleep. וכן ליצחק וכן ליעקב. Ve-chen le-Yitzchak ve-chen le-Yaakov. Okay, so
why they need אליהו Eliyahu to wake them up in general, you
know, what does that mean also? Does that mean that they wake
up their נשמות nishamas up in שמים? Or this might even be
suggesting something even more like a little more shocking, you know, even
within this context, that like he goes to מערת המכפלה Ma'arat haMachpelah
and he sort of wakes them up here down on earth. Anyway,
so why exactly he needs to be the one to wake them
up? I mean, I guess if it's talking about their dead bodies,
it makes sense.
But it sounds like the other rabbis aren't being woken up before.
We just read about it.
No, right, that's what I'm saying. But here he might be waking
up their dead bodies. Okay. אמר ליה ויש דוגמתם בעולם הזה? Amar
lei ve-yish dugmasam ba-olam hazeh? And so, and is there, you know,
is there some somebody comparable to them in terms of the power?
Did I skip a line? I must have skipped a line. וכן
ליעקב, Ve-chen le-Yaakov, I did. Okay. ולוקמינהו בהדי הדדי? Ve-ukeiminhu bahadi hadadi?
I knew I was missing a punchline. Why don't you wake them
all up at the same time so they can pray at the
same time? סברי דנפישי ברחמי, Savri de'nefishi berachamei, they will be too
powerful with their prayers if they're all praying at the same time.
ומייתי ליה למשיח בלא זמניה, U-maisei lei le-mashiach belo zamnei, and they'll
bring משיח Mashiach before its right time. So presumably what they're praying
for is they're praying for the redemption. Now exactly what this is
about in terms of ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, you know, it could
be that whole ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is the whole symbol of
future redemption, the waxing and the waning of the moon, right? So
anyway, so maybe they had a special תפילות tfillot on ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh for the redemption, but he wanted to make sure they
didn't do it all at the same time because then it would
have come too soon.
But it's every ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh?
Every ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh.
But the reason today was like though.
What? Today it was late. Well, I don't know, it was the
first ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh since he started coming. I don't know.
אמר ליה ויש דוגמתם בעולם... Amar lei yesh dugmasam ba-olam... I mean
it could be that ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is just by chance,
but it doesn't sound like that. It sounds like this was an
unusual occurrence. אמר ליה ויש דוגמתם בעולם הזה? Amar lei ve-yesh dugmasam
ba-olam hazeh? Are there is there somebody like them in this world
that has that power of prayer, or their combined power, because it
was three of them? אמר ליה איכא רבי חייא ובניו. Amar lei
ika Rabbi Chiya u-banav. So we're back to רבי Rebbi, חייא. Yes,
רבי Rebbi, חייא and his sons, their prayer would be as powerful
as the prayer of אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Avraham Yitzchak ve-Yaakov. So again,
you know, the power of רבי Rebbi. חייא. גזר רבי תעניתא, Gazar
Rebbe tanisa, so רבי Rebbi, said,
oh, great, let's try now to bring the משיח Mashiach in its,
you know, before its time, because now I know who who can
pray and make it happen. So he said we're going to have
a תענית, tanis,
because get everybody praying together and the power of everybody praying together.
אחתינו לרבי חייא ובניו, Achtinu le-Rabbi Chiya u-banav, and he had רבי
Rebbi חייא and his sons be the שליחי ציבור, shlichei tzibur, which
is very interesting. They're שליחי ציבור shlichei tzibur as a like, you
know, as a threesome. If you look at תוספות, Tosfos, look at
the תוספות Tosfos at פ״ו ע״א. pay-vav amud aleph. אחתינו לרבי חייא
ובניו. Achtinu le-Rabbi Chiya u-banav. ואף גב דתני במגילה אין מורידין לפני
התיבה לא מאנשי חיפה. Ve-af gav de-tani be-Megillah ein moridin lifnei ha-teivah
lo me'anshei Cheifa. Oh, that's a different point.
תוספות Tosfos says ואוקמינהו לפני התיבה, u-kaminhu lifnei ha-teivah, פ״ו ע״א, pay-vav
amud aleph, next stop. שלושתן, Shloshan, all three of them. כדאשכחן במדרש
דבתענית ציבור יורדין לפני התיבה שלושה. Ki de-ashchinan be-Midrash de-batanis tzibur yordin
lifnei ha-teivah shlosha. כדכתיב וירד... וידי משה כבדים ואהרן וחור Ki de-kasiv
vayayered... vayedei Moshe kaveidim ve-Aharon ve-Chur etc. then in a תענית tanis
you would actually have three people, I mean presumably only one would
say the שמונה
עשרה, Shmoneh Esreh, but you'd have three people there present leading the
ציבור. tzibur. Okay. So I had all
three of
them go down, רבי חייא ובניו. Rabbi Chiya u-banav. אמר משיב הרוח,
Amar mashiv ha-ruach, ונשבא זיקא, ve-nashva zika, the wind blew. Okay. אמר
מוריד הגשם, Amar morid ha-gashem, ואתא מיטרא, ve-asa mitra, the rain came,
which also is normally what you want when you're making a תענית
ציבור, tanis tzibur, it's for the rain. But רבי Rebbi wasn't just
interested in the rain. Okay. כי מטא למימר מחיה מתים, Ki mata
le-meimar mechayeh meisim, okay, he was about to say מחיה מתים mechayeh
meisim and that would have brought תחיית המתים techiyas ha-meisim and it
wasn't the right time. So רגש עלמא, ragash alma, the whole world
shook. אמרי ברקיעא, Amri birkiya, they said up in heaven, מאן גלי
רזיא בעלמא? man gali razia be-alma? And who who revealed this secret
in the world? That the power of the prayer of these three
people. אמרי אליהו. Amri Eliyahu. Okay, so they sort of reported on
אליהו, Eliyahu, they tattled. Okay. So they said אליהו. Eliyahu. אתיוהו לאליהו,
Aitu Eliyahu, they brought אליהו, Eliyahu, ומחיוהו שיתין פולסי דנורא. ve-machiu shishin
pulsei de-nura. They gave him 60 lashes of fire. There's the lashes
of fire. I don't know what you make of any of this.
No, I mean why 60? I don't know. אתא אידמי ליה כדובא
דנורא, Asa idmi lei ke-duva de-nura, and now אליהו Eliyahu had to
go correct this, right? This was all happening in a split second
before he got up to מחיה מתים. mechayeh meisim. So אליהו Eliyahu
went and he appeared to them like a bear of fire. I
don't know what the bear image is either. על בינייהו, Al beineihu,
he went among them, וטרדינהו, ve-tardinhu, and he distracted all of them
and scattered all of them. So broke up the whole davening before
they got to מחיה מתים. mechayeh meisim. Okay.
Okay, that's why he was late? He had to he had to
do all this.
No, he did all this when he meant. He was late because
he woke up אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Avraham Yitzchak ve-Yaakov. Once he revealed
this, then this was a new story that happened after. Okay. Okay.
Okay. Anyway, that’s another story but shows the power again of רבי
Rebbi חייא and the power of his prayer with that whole imagery
of the fire, etc. שמואל ירכינאה, Shmuel Yarchina'ah, שמואל, Shmuel, this is
just שמואל, Shmuel, the one we call שמואל. Shmuel. Why is he
called ירכינאה? Yarchina'ah? Some say רש״י Rashi says because he was because
he was you know a big astronomer and he knew about all
how to do ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and so on, which also
echoes the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh theme ירח, Yereach, right? ירח Yereach
is the moon. Okay, so שמואל Shmuel the lunar one or
something. אסיא דרבי הוה, Assia deRebbi hava, he was also, he was
like a real worldly man, right? An astronomer, a doctor, he was
like an early רמב״ם. Rambam. Okay, so anyway, he was רבי's Rebbi
doctor. So we’re now continuing here with רבי. Rebbi חלש רבי בעיניה,
Chalash Rebbi be'ayney, again the whole eye thing, a lot of themes
are repeated. רבי had a problem with his eye. אמרי אימלא לך
סמא, Amrei eimalach samah, he said should I put into it some
salve inside of the eye? אמרי לא יכילנא, Amrei lo yachilna, no
no I can't, it's too sensitive, I can't take salve in the
eye. אישטר לך משחא, Ishtelach mishra, should I put some type of
an ointment on top of your eye? אמרי לא יכילנא, Amrei lo
yachilna, no no I can't handle that. הוה מותיב ליה בגופסא דסמי
תותי בי סדיא, Hava motiv ley beguphsah de'samay tutei bei sadya, so
what he did is he put some type of a reed that
would, underneath the pillow, underneath the bed, and it would bring up
the fragrance of some type of a thing that he burned that
would be healing. ואיתסי, Ve'itasi, and רבי healed. הוה קא מצטער רבי
למסמכיה, Hava kamitzta'er Rebbi lemismachay, so now רבי wanted
to give שמואל Shmuel סמיכה smicha because שמואל Shmuel is never called
רב Rav so-and-so, שמואל Shmuel never received סמיכה. smicha. So here he
was his doctor, this huge worldly person with worldly knowledge, you know,
in sciences, being תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham,
רבי wanted to give him סמיכה. smicha. The irony is remember רבי
gave סמיכה smicha before to the guy who sold his body, the
son of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon, and here
he couldn't give שמואל Shmuel סמיכה, smicha, never worked out. רש״י Rashi
says for whatever reason, anytime he tried to get the sages together,
you couldn't get שמואל, Shmuel, when you got שמואל, Shmuel, you couldn't
get the sages together, somehow it never worked out.
But he did ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh?
Well yeah, but not as רבי, he never had סמיכה. smicha. ולא
הוה מסתייעא מילתא, Velo hava mistayia miltah, never worked out. אמר ליה
לא ליצטער מר,
Amar leh
lo listayar mar, שמואל Shmuel says the master, you, רבי, don't be
anguished that you can't give me סמיכה. smicha. בדידי חזי לי ספרא
דאדם הראשון, Bedidi chazi lee siphra de'adam harishon, I had a vision
of the book of אדם הראשון, Adam HaRishon, apparently רש״י Rashi says,
you know, this was like the book up in heaven in which
all the future generations are written out, like the history book before
history had happened. וכתיב ביה, Uchtiv bei, and it was written in
it, שמואל ירכינאה, Shmuel Yarchina'ah, שמואל Shmuel the lunar one, me, חכימי
יתקרי, chachami itkari, will be called the sage or wise person, ורבי
לא יתקרי, veRebbi lo yitkari, will never be called a רבי. Okay,
I will never get סמיכה, smicha, like okay, you know, it didn't
hurt him too much. שמואל Shmuel is one of the most quoted
אמוראים Amoraim in the גמרא. Gemara. The nice מהרש״א, Maharsha, the מהרש״א
Maharsha says we פסקן pasken like שמואל Shmuel in דיני ממונות dinei
mamonot and not in איסור והיתר. issur ve'heter. And the word חכם
chacham is often a word used in the context of דיני ממונות
dinei mamonot that somebody you know has to be has to be
a חכם chacham and so on, and by איסור והיתר issur ve'heter
the סמיכה smicha is יורה יורה yoreh yoreh to teach איסור והיתר.
issur ve'heter. So like the word that he's a חכם chacham and
not a רבי, this parallels that we פסקן pasken like him in
דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, right, monetary matters and not in classic like
ritual
matters. Okay, ואסו דרבי ואסו דרבי על ידותי תהוי, ve'asoo de'Rebbi ve'asoo
de'Rebbi al yadotay tehavy, and it also said that רבי's healing will
come through me, so that's a great merit that through me will
come your healing. So don't worry about it. I'm fine with what
I'm going to get. Okay. Now, רבי now we get a famous
famous line here for anybody for all the scholars who are interested
in how the תלמוד Talmud was like edited and the משנה Mishnah
was edited and arranged. So this is part of what שמואל Shmuel
sees written in this book up in heaven. So that was שמואל,
Shmuel, now we're going on to the next generation. רבי ורבי נתן
סוף משנה, Rebbi veRabbi Natan soph Mishnah, רבי and רבי נתן Rabbi
Natan are the end of the period of the משנה. Mishnah רב
אשי ורבינא סוף הוראה, Rav Ashi veRavina soph hora'ah, and רב אשי
Rav Ashi and רבינא Ravina are end of the period of teaching.
Now again, by the way, רב אשי Rav Ashi and רבינא Ravina
didn't exist yet in the time of שמואל, Shmuel, but okay, he's
looking at this pre-history book. Now what does this mean that רבי
and רבי נתן Rabbi Natan are the end of the משנה Mishna
period? It could just mean the Tannaic period, it could be it's
not even talking about the editing of the תלמוד Talmud or the
משנה Mishna at all. It could just say the period of the
תנאים Tannaim end with רבי and רבי נתן Rabbi Natan and the
period of the אמוראים, Amoraim, you know, end with רב אשי Rav
Ashi and רבינא. Ravina. But רש״י Rashi translates it very much into
this sort of editing process. So let's just read these very important
famous רש״י Rashi here. If you look at רש״י, Rashi, three lines
down, סוף משנה, soph Mishnah, סוף תנאים. soph Tannaim. Okay, so first
he just says they were end of the Tannaic period. עד ימיהם
לא אמרו איש את דבריו בבית המדרש היו תלמידים גורסים שמועה שמועה
לבדה. Ad yemeihem lo amru ish et devarav beveit hamidrash hayu talmidim
gorsim shemuah shemuah levada.
Until their time everybody would like just repeat their own traditional teaching.
ולא היו מסכתות סדורות, Velo hayu masekhtot sedurot,
and there was no order to them like everybody there would be
all these all these individual משניות, they weren't even physical right? They
were just oral teachings and everybody would have different sort of of
these oral teachings and there was no organization. וסידר וקיבץ ולא היו
מסכתות סדורות וסדר נקבץ על הסדר, Vesider vekibetz velo hayu masekhtot sedurot
veseder nikpatz al haseder,
there was nothing sort of organized.
והן כללו האמור בדורות שלפניהם, Vehen kalelu ha'amur bedorot she'lifneyhem, they organized
all the stuff that came before them, put it all together. וסידרו
המסכתות, Vesidru hamasekhtot, and they ordered it into different
tracts. Now רש״י *Rashi* says that actually there is some Mishnaic material
that's post רבי *Rebbe*. I don't know, the end of סוטה *Sotah*
says after רבי *Rebbe* died the ענווה *anavah* died in the world,
so that has to have been written after רבי *Rebbe*. Anyway, but
there is a little bit of Tannaic material. Basically the entire work
and effort and structure and organization all that was credited with רבי
*Rebbe*, apparently with רבי נתן *Rebbi Nassan* whose name we don't hear
that often but presumably he helped רבי *Rebbe* in that process. And
what's רבינא ורב אשי סוף הוראה *Ravina v'Rav Ashi sof hora'ah*? This
is even more interesting because this gets to the how the תלמוד
*Talmud* was written. סוף כל האמוראים *sof kol ha'Amoraim*, the end of
the Amoraitic period. עד ימיהם לא הייתה גמרא Gemara. על הסדר *ad
yimeihem lo haysah Gemara al haseder*. There was no organized גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* like the teaching associated with each משנה Mishnah *Mishna*. אלא כשהייתה
שאלה נשאלה בטעם המשנה בבית המדרש *ela k'shehaysah she'eilah nish'alah b'ta'am hamishna
b'veis hamidrash*. When
somebody said what's the reason for this משנה Mishna. *Mishna*? Like why
is there this opinion? What does so-and-so say? או שאלה על מעשה
המאורע בדין ממון או איסור והיתר *o she'eilah al ma'aseh hama'ora b'din
mamon o issur v'heter*. Or
somebody had a halachic question. כל אחד ואחד אומר omer, טעמו *kol
echad v'echad omer ta'amo*. So then there would be some discussion. You
have a halachic question, oh wait, maybe we can learn it out
from this משנה Mishna *Mishna*, let's discuss the applications etc. etc. Okay,
but it would all be very ad hoc and no sort of
you know consistent approach every single משנה *Mishna* organizing all the material
and so on. Okay. ורב אשי ורבינא סידרו שמועות אמוראים שלפניהם *v'Rav
Ashi v'Ravina sidru shmu'os Amoraim shelifneihem*. They organized all of the different
teachings that came before them. וקבעו על סדר מסכתות *v'kavu al seder
masechtos*. And they organized it according to the different tractates. Right? All
the discussions relating to this משנה *Mishna* they put on this משנה
*Mishna*, etc. כל אחד ואחד אצל המשנה הראויה והשנויה לה *kol echad
v'echad eitzel hamishna harauyah v'hashnuyah lah*. Everyone associated with its relevant משנה
*Mishna*. So they organized the pre-existing material. And not only that, והקשו
קושיות שיש להשיב ופירוקים שראויים לתרץ *v'hikshu kushyos she'yeish l'hashiv u'feirukim she'reuyim
l'taretz*. And they also, after they organized the material, they continued the
discussion. And they said wait a minute, what about this question? What
about this? How do you deal with that? How do you do
that? So they actually added the final layer. They didn't just organize
like רבי *Rebbe*, but they added the final layer of the discussion
and of the text. הם אמוראים שבימיהם וקבעו הכל בגמרא *hem Amoraim
shebimeihem v'kavu hakol ba'Gemara*. And they put it all in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. כגון *k'gon*. Now
רש״י *Rashi* is basically going to tell you here is what רבינא
ורב אשי *Ravina v'Rav Ashi* did. When you see a גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* say איתיבי *eiseivei*, I'll ask you, מיתיבי *meiseivei*, רמינהו *raminhu*, איבעיא
להו *iba'ya l'hu*. Okay, all those, what about this? What about that?
You know those key words. So basically what רש״י *Rashi* is saying
is that רבינא ורב אשי *Ravina v'Rav Ashi* are the סתם *Stam*.
They're the anonymous voice. They organized all the stuff before and then
they asked all these other questions and they provided the anonymous voice.
Now scholars disagree with this. Not only scholars, they say the anonymous
voice, well they say pieces maybe became earlier, but mostly the anonymous
voice came even after רבינא ורב אשי *Ravina v'Rav Ashi*. And actually
there's the famous letter called the אגרת רב Rav שרירא גאון *Igeres
Rav Sherira Gaon*. That רב שרירא גאון *Rav Sherira Gaon* was asked
about how the whole משנה *Mishna* and גמרא Gemara *Gemara* were written.
And he writes this long letter, or whatever, not letter because it
wasn't written, but this long letter where he describes it. And he
basically quotes this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. And he basically says not like
רש״י *Rashi*. רש״י *Rashi* makes it sound like everything was so scattered,
they did the same organizing thing. You don't get that sense when
you read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. You get the sense when you
read the גמרא *Gemara* that actually they would learn משנה על הסדר
*Mishna al haseder* and have discussions על הסדר *al haseder*. So anyway,
so he, you know, רב שרירא גאון *Rav Sherira Gaon* makes it
sound more like there was
a layering. Like, you know, you have one generation and they have
their contribution, the next generation came and they added their contribution. But
it was basically still ordered according to the order of the מסכתות
*masechtos* and the משניות *mishnayos*. And then רבינא ורב אשי *Ravina v'Rav
Ashi*, he says, were the last הוראה *hora'ah*. They gave the last
halachic contributions to the גמרא *Gemara*. And then the רבנן סבוראי *Rabanan
Savorai* that came later, they had discussions in the גמרא *Gemara*, but
they were never really of a halachic nature. Actually, anyway, they point
out like for example the first סוגיא *sugya* of קידושין *Kiddushin*, you
know, goes all of these things about like about like why does
it say מקודשת *mekudeshes* and why does it say ניקנית *nikneis* and
not מקודשת *mekudeshes* and why לשון זכר *lashon zachar* and לשון נקבה
*lashon nekeivah*? And asks all these like technical grammar questions without introducing
any new halachic material. Just drawing on pre-existing halachic material. You also
have something similar in the beginning of בבא קמא *Bava Kamma*. So
basically he says the רבנן *Rabanan* after this, layers were added, but
no new halachic material was added. That's how רב שרירא גאון *Rav
Sherira Gaon* says it. Okay, but now to finish רש״י *Rashi* says
like this.
I'm sorry. So according to רש״י *Rashi*, רבי *Rebbe*, רבי
*Rebbe*'s role and according to רב שרירא גאון *Rav Sherira Gaon*, that
was the same, but just רבינא ורב אשי *Ravina v'Rav Ashi*? Yeah,
yeah, they're basically debating the word of רבינא ורב אשי *Ravina v'Rav
Ashi*.
Okay. So איבעיא להו בתר דתרצו כל מאי דשיירו אותם שלפניהם *iba'ya
l'hu basar d'tirtzu kol mai d'shayu osam shelifneihem* and they gave the
answers what was not done by those that preceded them. ואותם שאמרו
לפניהם הקושיות והתירוצים עליהם ולא קבעו בגמרא על סדר המסכתות ועל המשנה
שסידר רבי *v'osam she'amru lifneihem hakushyos v'hatirutzim aleihem v'lo kavu ba'Gemara al
seder hamasechtos v'al hamishna she'sider Rebbe*. And even questions that were asked
before that were not put in their right place. ובא רב אשי
ורבינא וקבעו מהם *u'va Rav Ashi v'Ravina v'kavu mehem*. And they put
in their right place. So they organized all the material and then
they added this final layer. Okay, so that's a very important take
about what רבינא ורב אשי *Ravina v'Rav Ashi* did. And that leads
a lot of ראשונים *Rishonim* to assume that רבינא ורב אשי *Ravina
v'Rav Ashi* were the authors of the סתם *Stam*. But as I
said, that's not what the scholars assume and it's not so much
what like this אגרת רב שרירא גאון *Igeres Rav Sherira Gaon* says
either. Okay, back to the גמרא *Gemara*. That was a nice little.
I mean that layer even during the סבוראים *Saboraim*? Yeah, there, yeah,
exactly, but they might say that there were סתם *Stam* elements even
before. Like it might have been the סתם *Stam* was not just
a final layer. Maybe it's not clear that there was an actual
cut-off. רבינא *Ravina* and רב אשי *Rav Ashi* according to רב שרירא
גאון *Rav Sherira Gaon* did organize everything until then, but just not...
no, no, רב שרירא גאון *Rav Sherira Gaon*, no, what רב שרירא
גאון *Rav Sherira Gaon* is saying does not... רש"י *Rashi* assigns them
a whole organizing role, but רב שרירא גאון *Rav Sherira Gaon* does
not say that. He basically says the structure was there from רבי
*Rebbe* and the other generations just kept on sort of adding to
it. I mean even רש"י *Rashi*, they were just the end of
the הוראה *Hora'ah*. They didn't do any major editing process. That's the
way רש"י *Rashi* reads it. They were just the last halakhic contribution
to the גמרא *Gemara*. Okay, so it says like this: וסימנך עד
אבא אל מקדשי *Usimanach ad ava el mikdashei*. That's רב אשי *Rav
Ashi*. אבין לאחריתם *Avin l'achritam*. That's רבינא *Ravina*. So רבינא *Ravina* and
רב אשי *Rav Ashi*. Okay, until the... that's the end, לאחריתם *l'achritam*,
the end of the process. אמר רב כהנא אשתעי לי רב חמא
בר ברתא דחמא רבה בר נחמני Rabbah bar Nachmani, *Amar Rav Kahana
ishta'ei li Rav Chama bar Barta dechama Rabbah bar Nachmani*. So רב
חמא *Rav Chama*, the son of the daughter of רב חמא *Rav
Chama*, רבה Rabbah בר נחמני *Rabbah bar Nachmani*. He said to me
the following: רבה Rabbah בר נחמני *Rabbah bar Nachmani*, who is רבה
Rabbah *Rabbah*, when we say רבה Rabbah *Rabbah* in the גמרא *Gemara*,
it's רבה Rabbah בר נחמני *Rabbah bar Nachmani*. So רבה Rabbah *Rabbah*,
אגב שמדא דנח נפשיה *agav shmada de'nach nafshia*, because of some decree
of the government, he ultimately brought about his death. What happened? Now,
what this is doing about anything before, it's not clear except we're
talking about the great rabbis, רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiya*, רבי חנינא *Rabbi
Chanina*, יהושע בר רס *Yehoshua bar Ras*. So we're going to tell
some other great story about a great rabbi. So רבה Rabbah, *Rabbah*,
because of some decree of the government, that brought about his death.
What was the story? אזלו בי כורצא בי מלכא *Azlu bei kortza
bei malka*. There were people that were slandering the Jews in the
house of the king. Maybe fellow Jews. אמרו *Amru*, and they said:
איכא חד גברא ביהודאי *Ika chad gavra bi'huda'ei*, there's one person among
the Jews דקא מבטל תריסר אלפי גברי מישראל ירחי בקייטא וירחי בסיתווא
*deka m'vatel treisar alfei gavrei mi'yisrael yarchei bekaita veyarchei besitvah*. He makes
12,000 Jews not do their work, one month in the summer and
one month in the fall. Because this is basically the month before
פסח *Pesach* and the month before סוכות *Sukkot*, and they are spending
a month coming to ישיבה *yeshiva*, everybody took off work and there
was a whole month that was called ירחי כלה *Yarchei Kalla*, right?
And they were doing this learning in ישיבה *yeshiva*, and they said,
"Yeah, but then we're not collecting taxes from them during those months."
Presumably, they would collect taxes on a monthly basis. Okay, and they
were saying, "So it's a big problem, lowering the productivity, we're not
collecting the taxes." Okay, so...
ירחי בקייטא וירחי בסיתווא *yarchei bekaita veyarchei besitvah*, מכרגא דמלכא *mikarga demalka*.
And they are making them, they are taking them away from paying
the king's tax, the king's poll tax. שדרו פריסתקא דמלכא בתריה *Shadru
pristaka demalka batrei*.
So they sent a king's messenger or officer to go seize רבה
Rabbah, *Rabbah*, ולא אשכחיה *v'lo ashkchei*, they couldn't find him.
ערק araik, ואזל מפומבדיתא לאקרא מאקרא לאגמא מאגמא לשחין משחין לצריפא לעינא
דמים *Arka v'azal
mi'pumbedita l'akra mi'akra l'agma mi'agma l'shchin mi'shchin l'tzrifa l'eina damim*. He went
from one place to the next, one village to the next, and
then he went back from לעינא דמים *Eina Damim* to פומבדיתא *Pumbedita*,
running away from this officer from the king. בפומבדיתא be-Pumbedisa אשכחיה *Be'Pumbedita
ashkchei*. And he was discovered in פומבדיתא *Pumbedita*. How was he discovered?
By the following case: איקלע פריסתקא דמלכא לההוא אושפיזא דרבה *Ikla pristaka
demalka l'ahu ushpiza d'rabbah*. So this king's officer came to the אושפיזא
*ushpiza* that רבה Rabbah, *Rabbah* was staying at, and presumably, one way
to understand this is he didn't realize yet רבה Rabbah *Rabbah* was
there. He was just running after trying to find רבה *Rabbah*, he
happened to chance at the same אושפיזא *ushpiza*. קרבו תכא קמיה *Kirbu
takka kamei*. The owners of the אושפיזא *ushpiza* brought a plate in
front of him of food. ואשקיוהו תרי כסי *v'ashkyu trei kasei*. And
they gave him two cups of wine or beer, whatever it was.
מדליו תכא מקמיה *Medalu takka mi'kamei*. And they removed the plate. הדר
פרצופיה לאחוריה *Hadar partzufei l'achorei*. And what happened was his face got
turned around, got turned backwards, whatever happened, like, you know. So because
the point is is that the idea of doubles, pairs, so it
was two cups of wine for the whole meal, is something that
exposes somebody to the acts of the שדים *shedim*, of the demons.
So this officer, unintentional to the owners of the אושפיזא *ushpiza*, they
weren't paying attention, you know, he drank these two cups of wine
and he was attacked by שדים *shedim* and this thing happened to
his face. Okay, so far presumably he didn't realize that רבה *Rabbah*
was there, presumably. Okay. אמרו ליה amru lei, *Amru lei*: מאי נעביד
ליה גברא דמלכא הוא *Mai na'avad lei gavra demalka hu*. So the
owners of the אושפיזא *ushpiza* went to רבה *Rabbah*, who presumably was
hiding, and they said to him, "What are we going to... what
with this king... this person, what can we do to help him?
He's a king's officer, you know, how... we need to help him
out." אמר להו *Amar lehu*, he said to them: קרבו תכא קמיה
*Kirbu takka kamei*, put the plate back, which presumably will make it
a continuation of the meal. Okay, מקמיה *mi'kamei*. ואשקיוהו חד כסא *v'ashkyu
chad kassa*. And give him another cup of wine. מדליו תכא מקמיה
*Medalu takka mi'kamei*. And then remove the plate. So now he's had
three cups at one meal and not two. By bringing the plate
back, it makes it a continuation. Okay. ואיתסי *v'itsei*. And then he'll
be healed. עבדו ליה הכי ואיתסי *Avdu lei hachi v'itsei*. They did
and he was healed. אמר *Amar*, so now this officer realized, you
know, how did he get healed? Somebody here must know, must be
very wise. I bet רבה *Rabbah* is hiding out here. Like that's,
you know. That's I mean it's clear from the story that's what's
happening, but I think that's implied, that's what the מהרש"א Maharsha says.
אמר מידע ידענא דגברא דבעינא הכא. Amar meida yadana degavra d'beina hacha.
Ah, I know the person I'm looking for is here. מאן? Man?
Who? בחיש. bachish. Who? That is he. הכא. hacha. בחיש בתריה, bachish
batrei, he searched for him, ואשכחיה, v'ashchei, he found him. אמר, but
of course he was very grateful because he healed him. So he
said, אזלינא מהכא, azlina me'hacha, I'm going to leave here, אי קטלי
קטלו לההוא גברא, ee katli katlu lahu gavra, and I'll say I
couldn't find you. אי קטלי קטלו לההוא גברא, ee katli katlu lahu
gavra, if they actually execute me, לא מגלינא, lo maglina, I won't
reveal where you're hiding.
ואי נגדי, v'ee negidi, but if they actually torture me, מנגדין ליה,
minagdin lei, if they, but if they torture me, then מגלינא, maglina,
then I'll reveal it. I can't withstand torture, right? Very, very human
and understanding, right? That torture can be worse than death. Okay. So
אייתויה לקמיה, ayituya kemei, so they brought רבה in front of him.
עיילוה לאדרונא, ailu l'adruna, they put him into a room, וטרקוה לבבא
באנפיה, v'tarkei l'babah b'anpei, and they locked the door in his presence.
Now, it's not exactly clear to me, I didn't see the מהרש"א
didn't explain either. If he was going to go back to the
king and say he couldn't find him, why did they have to
lock רבה in a room, right? Like you know, so I don't
know. Maybe he was like... I have no idea. But anyway... maybe
if he got tortured then they would find where רבה was and
I don't know. Anyway... okay, anyway but רבה was being locked in
a room. בעי רחמי, Ba'i rachamei, רבה prayed, פקע אשיתא, paka ashita,
the door burst, broke down. ערק, so רבה ran away again ואזל
לאגמא. v'azal l'agma. He went back to אגמא, agma, which is one
of the places he was before. הוה יתיב אגדרא דדיקלא, Havei yasiv
agidra d'dikla, he was sitting on a chopped down palm tree, וקא
גרס, veka gars, and he was learning. קא מיבעיא במתיבתא דרקיעא. Kamib'ei
b'mivta d'rakiya. Now, up in heaven, a debate was going on. We're
back to the heavenly court. Okay, another very famous גמרא. There was
the following debate that was going up in the heavenly court. אם
בהרת קודמת לשער לבן טמא. Im baheret kodemat l'se'ar lavan tamei. The
משנה teaches that if the, you know, the תורה says that if
a person has a white hair of צרעת, tzara'at, they're טמא, tamei,
but if the... then if the whole... if there becomes a like
a spot of white, you know, that sorts of spreads over the
body, whatever, then the person is טהור. tahor. So it matters what
the order is. אם בהרת קודמת לשער לבן טמא, Im baheret kodemat
l'se'ar lavan tamei, he's טמא. tamei. ואם שער לבן קודם לבהרת, Ve'im
se'ar lavan kodem labaheret, but if the white, I'm sorry, I said
that wrong. I was thinking about something else. It says that if
a person has a white spot, and then it says and if
a white hair emerges from the white spot, then it's צרעת. tzara'at.
Okay, so the משנה teaches but if the white hair was there
first and the white spot came afterwards, it's not צרעת. tzara'at. אם
בהרת קודמת לשער לבן טמא, Im baheret kodemat l'se'ar lavan tamei, ואם
שער לבן קודם לבהרת, v'im se'ar lavan kodem labaheret, if the white
hair came first, טהור, tahor, and then the and then the spot
on the skin he's טהור. tahor. ספק, Safek, now what if it's
a doubt, which one came first? So קודשא בריך הוא Kudsha Berich
Hu אומר, טהור. tahor. God says it would be טהור. tahor. וכולהו
מתיבתא דרקיעא v'chulu mivta d'rakiya אמרי, amrei, טמא. tamei. They said it
would be טמא. tamei. Now it's interesting because, you know, you heard
before about the heavenly court. I wonder like is the heavenly court
made up of angels or is the heavenly court made up of
all the dead rabbis, right? Because before we heard the rabbis were
going up to heavenly court. So here you have like God arguing
with the rabbis. Okay, and you know there's a lot to do
with this גמרא. Like what does this mean about ספק? safek? You
know, because like there's another גמרא that says, right, מי איכא ספיקא
קמי שמיא, Mika sefeka kamei shemaya, right? Is there ever any doubt
as far as heaven is concerned? You know, so to a little
bit it says like, you know, God, you know, who knows everything,
like He can look at a case of doubt or whatever, you
know, and He can sort of, you know, He's going to weigh
in favor of things being טהור. tahor. We as human beings, we
don't know how to deal with doubt. It's our human fra... you
know, it's our human, you know, the fact that we're limited as
humans, we don't know how to deal with doubt, so what? We're
going to have to play it safe and we're going to have
to say טמא, tamei, right? But that sort of brings more טומאה
tumah to the world as it were, you know? But like that's
sort of the human condition. Okay, anyway so this was the debate
that was going on. ואמרי, V'amrei, they said, מאן מוכח? man mocha?
Who can we call on that will sort of decide this case?
To decide between God and the... the deciding vote. Okay. It's sort
of like... it's sort of like, you know they tell a story
with Abraham Lincoln, that he took a vote in his cabinet and
he said ay and everybody else said nay, so he said one
ay, ten nays, the ays have it. So anyway, okay. So it's
God against everybody else but we need a deciding vote. Who's going
to be the deciding vote? נוכח רבה בר נחמני. Nochi Rabbah bar
Nachmani. Okay, let's get רבה בר נחמני, he'll be our deciding vote.
Of course he was still alive, he couldn't join the heavenly academy
until he died. Okay. דאמר רבה בר נחמני, D'amar רבה bar נחמני,
now how do we know that he should be the deciding vote?
Well, look what he says about himself. He said, אני יחיד בנגעים
אני יחיד באהלות. Ani yachid b'nega'im ani yachid b'ohalos. I am the
most, you know, the greatest authority in issues of נגעים, nega'im, of
spots of leprosy, in issues of אהלות, ohalos, of טומאה. tumah. So
רבה, you're the greatest authority, come up here to heaven and help
us decide our case. שדרו שליחא בתריה. Shadru shelicha batrei. It's so
wonderful, the same way the king sent a messenger to go find
רבה, right, the heavenly court, the divine king is sending a messenger
also to basically kill רבה, bring רבה up to heaven. Okay. לא
הוה מצי מלאך המות למיקרב ליה. Lo hava matzi malach hamaves l'mikrav
lei. Now the מלאך המות malach hamaves couldn't get close to him.
Why? מדלא הוה פסיק פומיה מגירסא. mi d'lo hava pasik pumei migirsa.
Because he would never stop learning. Okay, the same story. Same story
as King David. אדהכי, Ad'hachi, נשב זיקא, Nashav zika, but then a
wind blew, ואביש ביני קני, Va-aveish beinei kanei, and it and it
made some noise between the like the the the reeds, סבר גונדא
דפרשי הוא somar gunda de-parshi hu and Rabba said oh my god
it must be the king's troops are coming to seize me because
remember that story hadn't exactly finished. אמר תינח נפשי דהוא גברא, Amar
teinach nafshi de-hu gavra, he Rabba said I rather should I should
die, it's interesting just because he interrupted to say it's the king's
troops you would have thought the מלאך המות Malach ha-Maves would have
got him at that second but it's actually a better story because
he actually sort of willingly went to his death. He said I
should die ולא ימסר בידא דמלכותא ve-lo yimsar be-yada de-malchusa rather than
being given over to the kingdom, to the government. Okay because maybe
he was afraid of being tortured or whatever. So כי הוה נח
נפשיה, ki avei na'ach nafshai, אמר, so as he was dying so
then the מלאך המות Malach ha-Maves took him and he was dying,
okay and he said טהור טהור. tahor tahor. So he actually as
he was dying they needed his vote right away. So so as
he was dying so before Rabba, what do you say, what's the
פסק? psak? He said טהור טהור. tahor tahor. Okay by the way
notice that he sided here with God, right? Okay. יצתה בת קול
ואמרה Yas'a bas kol ve-amrah heavenly voice came out and said אשריך
רבה בר נחמני ashreicha Rabba bar Nachmani praise you Rabba bar Nachmani
שגופך טהור she-gufcha tahor your body is pure ויצתה נשמתך בטהרה ve-yatz'a
nishmascha be-tahara and your and your soul departed with the word טהור.
tahor. Okay now by the way I just want to show you
something hilarious if you look at the second line of the גמרא
when we read it before the second wide line where it said
מתיבתא דרקיעא אמרי טמא mesivta de-raki'a amri tamei the heavenly court says
it's טמא. tamei. You see that there's a little ב beis there
by the word טמא tamei which indicates that that's how we פוסקין.
pasken. So God and Rabba said טהור tahor and we פוסקין להלכה
טמא. pasken la-halacha tamei. Okay because it's actually in a משנה in
נגעים Nega'im the actual anonymous voice is טמא. tamei. Okay and it's
only a דעת יחיד das yachid a single rabbi who says טהור
tahor which again is that beautiful idea you know about about you
know humans פוסקין paskening against God, right? So it's like a wonderful
irony they got Rabba to have the deciding vote up in heaven
but here down on earth we wound up פוסקין paskening with the
human vote. Okay. נפל פתקא מרקיעא בפומבדיתא Nafal piska mi-raki'a be-Pumbedisa by
the way there's also a tremendous parallel between this story and the
famous story of the תנור של עכנאי Tanur shel Achnai everybody remember
the תנור של עכנאי Tanur shel Achnai right with רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer and the bending walls of the בית מדרש Beis Midrash right
and they were also debating and Rabbi and everybody else were saying
טמא tamei and he was saying טהור. tahor. And actually the follow
up story of that is that when he was dying the rabbis
came but he was in חרם cherem so they couldn't get too
close to his bed so they stayed outside four אמות amos from
his bed or whatever and they said you know you know they
asked him are you going to retract your position and finally concede
to what everybody else said? And he said no you know I
stick to my position and it was טהור tahor right? And then
it says if I remember correctly it says the same ending his
you know his soul departed with the word טהור. tahor. So it's
exactly sort of the same thing of the human sort of control
of תורה deciding against God right and the person here who's sort
of siding with God sort of saying טהור tahor and dying but
maybe like you know not fit for this world. It's a very
powerful parallel between those stories. Okay now the גמרא says like this.
נפל פתקא מרקיעא Nafal piska mi-raki'a a a little פתק petek like
a little like piece of paper like came out of heaven בפומבדיתא
in Pumbedisa it descended from heaven in Pumbedisa and it said on
it the following thing: רבה בר נחמני אתבקש במתיבתא דרקיעא. Rabba bar
Nachmani isvakesh bi-mesivta de-raki'a. Rabba bar Nachmani was called up to the
heavenly בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. Okay they needed him to give שיעור
shiur up in the heavenly בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. נפקו אביי ורבא
Nafaku Abaye ve-Rava anyway so he died. נפקו אביי ורבא וכולהו רבנן
לאיעסוקי ביה Nafaku Abaye ve-Rava ve-chulhu rabbanan le-isvukei lei so Abaye and
Rava and all the rabbis went out to take care of his
body and to bury him but ולא הוו ידעי דוכתיה lo havu
yadei duchtei they didn't know where he was. Remember he had been
in hiding from the government. אזלו אגמא חזו ציפרי דמטלי וקיימי Azlu
agma chazu tziparei de-metallelei ve-kaimei and they went to אגמא Agma the
place where he was hiding and they saw birds that were providing
you know shading over a space and just hovering in one part.
אמרי שמע מינה התם הוא Amri shema mina hasam hu he must
be there and they're protecting his body so presumably though they couldn't
get to his body but they knew that that's where he was.
So ספדוהו תלתא יומי safduhu slasa yomei they eulogized him for three
days ותלתא לילוותא ve-slasa leilvosei and three nights. נפל פתקא Nafal piska
and another heavenly sort of piece of paper came down and said
כל הפורש יהא בנידויו kol ha-poresh yehei be-niduyei anybody who stops you
haven't done enough. Anybody who who stops the eulogizing will be in
חרם. cherem. So ספדוהו שבעה יומי safduhu shiva yomei so they went
for seven days. נפל פתקא לכלו לביתכם לשלום Nafal piska le-chulu be-seichem
le-shalom finally now another heavenly thing came out: go home you're done
okay you're done showing him proper respect. ההוא יומא דנח נפשיה Ha-hu
yoma de-nach nafshai that day that he died דליא זעפא dalya za'afa
a heavenly wind came okay ודרי ליהוא טייא ve-darei le-hahu taya and
lifted up a like an Arab, טייא taya is like an Arab
nomad like on his camel כי רכיב גמלא ki rachi gamla when
he was riding on his camel מהאי גיסא דנהר פפא mi-hai gisa
de-nahar pappa he lifted him up on one end of the נהר
פפא Nahar Pappa ושדיי בהאי גיסא ve-shadei be-hai gisa and threw him
onto the other side of of the river Pappa. Now presumably this
is because there's this heavenly anger. That, you know, Rava was not
buried. I mean, it's a question like did they really have a
choice, right? They did what they could do, but it seems like
anyway, since he didn't get the full respect that could have been
given to him. אמרי Amri said, מאי האי? mai hai? What's going
on? אמרי ליה, Amri lei, so people said to him, נח נפשיה
דרבה בר נחמני. nach nafsheih d'Rabba bar Nachmani. Rabba bar Nachmani died
and things are all a tumult in the world. So אמר לפניו,
amar l'fanav, so the Arab now is praying. רבונו של עולם, Master
of the World, very frum sounding Arab. כולי עלמא דידך הוא. kulei
alma didach hu. He actually speaks Aramaic, this Arab. The whole world
belongs to you. ורבה בר נחמני דידך הוא, v'Rabba bar Nachmani didach
hu, and you now and Rabba bar Nachmani is yours and you
now have him. אנת דרבה ורבה דידך. ant d'Rabba v'Rabba didach. You
are your pals with Rabba, Rabba's pals with you, or you have
Rabba, Rabba has you, the two of you are together now. אמאי
קמחרבת ליה לעלמא? amai ka m'charvat lei l'alma? Why are you destroying
the world? Okay, it's a terrible thing that he died or whatever,
but I mean it's not clear what God's upset that Rabba was
dead, like what's the anger about, what was exactly was this response
about, like I really don't know. Anyway, נח זעפיה, nach zafyah, so
the anger calmed down. Rabbi Shimon now, one last story of all
these stories, which doesn't seem to be... what about the shaking was
the... oh, the shaking of the of the of the rushes, right.
No, but there was the shaking when the three when Rabbi... oh,
when they were praying, Rabbi Chiya and his sons were praying and
the world was shaking because the world was disturbed. That's a good
point too. Okay. Rabbi Shimon ben Chalafta, now Rabbi Shimon ben Chalafta
בעל בשר הוה, baal basar hava, he was very he was very
overweight. Corpulent would be a good translation. יומא חד הוי חמימא ליה,
yoma chad hava chamima lei, one day it was very hot. הוה
סליק ויתיב אשינא דטורא. hava salik v'yativ a'shina d'tura. He would sit
at the top of like of a rock of a mountain. אמר
לה לברתיה, amar lah l'varteih, he would say to his daughter, בתי
הניפי עלי במניפא, bitti hanifi alai b'manifa, you know, fan me with
a fan to cool me off. ואני אתן לך כרין דנרד. v'ani
etten lach karin d'nerd. I will give you like bundles of nard,
which is some aromatic, you know, herb or whatever. אדהכי נשבא זיקא,
ad'hacha nashba zika, while he was waiting for her to do it,
a wind came and it was cooled him off. אמרי כמה כרין
דנרד למרי דזיקא. amri kamma karin d'nerd l'mari d'zika. How many nard,
how many bundles of this of this herb now do I have
to give to the owner of the wind? Now I have to
owe it all to God. So like what did that have to
do with anything? So you could say it's got some of the
wind theme going on here. Rashi also says it ends with the
whole discussion about, it's a little funny to say this, but before
we were discussing, remember way back in the beginning, these very overweight
rabbis, right? How they that discussed like two days ago, so now
we're ending somehow the discussion with an overweight rabbi. I don't I
can't really explain it. Okay. הכל כמנהג המדינה, hakol k'minhag hamedina, go
back for a moment to some halachic discussion. Okay, when you make
a stipulation with the workers, it goes by whatever the practices are
of the country. So הכל לאתויי מאי? hakol l'atuyei mai? What does
it come to include? לישנא דאשלי דנהיגי מחריך ריפתא ומישתא. lishana d'ashli
d'nahigi machrich rifta u'mishta. In a place where they have the practice
that you would basically give them some bread and drink. אנפקא דאנפקא.
anpaka d'anpaka. And they would do it... what does the word anpaka
mean again? Hold on. What does Rashi say? Oh, no, in a
in a certain in a vessel that holds a revi'is. Okay, like
in a that they would give them they would give them some
bread and drink, you know, in a certain a certain a measure
of drink. So okay, so what does הכל כמנהג המדינה hakol k'minhag
hamedina mean? דאמר להו קדימו ואייתי לכו. d'amar lehu kdimu v'aitai l'chu.
If he says to them, now there's two interpretations of this, one
is either I want you to come early and have your meal,
your breakfast, before the work starts. Okay, I don't want you to
be eating on my time, I want you to have your I'll
give you the breakfast, but I want to give I'm going to
give it to you early, before the day starts. So אמרו ליה,
they can say לאו כל כמינך. lav kol kminach. I'm sorry, you
don't have the right to do that. The standard practice is we
get the breakfast after the working hours have begun. Tosfos says another
version which is basically that they would normally take a break and
go back to the main house and get their and get their
snack. And he said no, you stay at your work, I'll bring
it to you. So don't you know so you don't have to
take off of your work. And they say no, we have a
right to actually do what the minhag is and take our break
and to go have it at the house. Okay, מעשה ברבי יוחנן
בן מתיא שאמר לבנו צא ושכור לנו פועלים. maaseh b'Rabbi Yochanan ben
Matya she'amar l'vno tze u'schor lanu poalim. So there was a story
that he told his kids, you know, hire for us workers, he
promised to pay them food, and then he said, oh my god,
then you're gonna have to give them huge feasts because they're בני
אברהם יצחק ויעקב. bnei Avraham, Yitzchak, v'Yaakov. So go change the terms
of the agreement. So the Gemara says מעשה לסתור? maaseh l'stur? This
story contradicts, because we said it's הכל כמנהג המדינה. hakol k'minhag hamedina.
And here he's saying that if you promised them you have to
give them a huge feast. So the Gemara says no, חסורי מחסרא
והכי קתני. chasuri m'chasra v'hachi katani. It's missing words, here's how you
teach it. ואי פסק להו מזוני. v'ei pasak lehu mezoni. If it
was already the practice to give them food and then you explicitly
stipulated to feed them, then עריב להו. ariv lehu. That explicit stipulation
means that you're going to provide for them more than the norm.
Okay. Now how much more is not clear, but now we have
a story that at least Rabbi Yochanan ben Matya understood that the
more would be would be like almost infinite, would be enormous. ומעשה
נמי ברבי יוחנן בן מתיא שאמר לבנו צא ושכור לנו פועלים הלכו
ופסק להם מזונות וכשבא אצל אביו אמר לו בני אפילו אתה עושה
להם כסעודת שלמה בשעתו. u'maaseh nami b'Rabbi Yochanan ben Matya she'amar l'vno
tze u'schor lanu poalim halchu v'pasak lahem mezonot u'cheshba etzel aviv amar
lo bni afilu ata oseh lahem k'seudat Shlomo b'shaato. He went and
he agreed to give food and when he returned to his father,
his father said, my son, even if you make for them like
the feast of Solomon in his time. Even if you make for
them feasts like שלמה Shlomo when he was at his height of
his kingdom, לא יצאת ידי חובתך, lo yatzata yedei chovasecha, you wouldn't
fulfill your obligation עמהם, imahem, שהם בני אברהם יצחק ויעקב, she-heim benei
Avraham Yitzchak ve-Yaakov, that the sons of אברהם, Avraham, יצחק, Yitzchak, and
יעקב. Yaakov. Now that doesn't mean then the other rabbis say no,
הכל כמנהג המדינה. hakol keminhag hamedina. You know, it may be more
but not that much more, or maybe even when you say that
you're going to give them and you're explicit, it never really exceeds
what the norm is. Yeah, that was just quoting the משנה. Oh,
that was just explaining the context of the משנה was even though
הכל כמנהג המדינה, hakol keminhag hamedina, at least according to this approach,
if you explicitly stipulate, then you have to give more. And this
interpretation of more would mean you'll never fulfill your obligation. So now
the גמרא is going to have some more אגדתא Agadata because now
we're saying that שלמה Shlomo had big feasts, and אברהם, Avraham, יצחק,
Yitzchak, and יעקב Yaakov had even bigger feasts than שלמה Shlomo because
their children deserve a bigger feast than שלמה. Shlomo. Okay, so the
גמרא says like this: למימרא דסעודתיה דאברהם אבינו עדיפא מדשלמה? lemeimra deseudateih
de-Avraham Avinu adifa mideshlomo? You're telling me אברהם's Avraham feast was bigger
than שלמה? Shlomo? והכתיב, ve-haktiv, it says by שלמה: Shlomo: ויהי לחם
שלמה ליום אחד שלשים כור סלת, vayehi lechem Shlomo leyom echad sheloshim
kor solet, שלמה's Shlomo bread for one day was 30 כור, kor,
you know, 30 whatever, you know, huge measures of fine flour, וששים
כור קמח, ve-shishim kor kemach, and 60 measures of more bran flour,
עשרה בקר בריאים, asara bakar beri'im, 10 healthy cattle, ועשרים בקר רעי,
ve-esrim bakar re'i, and 20 cattle grazing out in the pasture, ומאה
צאן, u-meah tzon, and 100 sheep, לבד מאיל וצבי ויחמור, levad me-ayal
u-tzvi ve-yachmur, these different types of wild animals, you know, gazelles, etc.,
וברבורים אבוסים, u-varburim abusim, and stuffed fowl, or stuffed—what's a ברבור barbur
nowadays is what, is it a goose? I always forget from here
whether it's the goose or the duck. Does anybody know? They—okay anyway,
it's either a goose or a duck, I forget what it is
in modern Hebrew. I would say אבוסים. abusim. Yeah. Yeah, they say
אבוסים abusim hens. Hens? Stuffed hens? Okay, anyway, in modern Hebrew ברבור
barbur is I think a duck or a goose, I just don't
remember which. Okay, ואמר גוריון בן אסטיון משמיה דרב, ve-amar Guryon ben
Astiyon mishmeih de-Rav, and גוריון בן אסטיון Guryon ben Astiyon said in
the name of רב said: הללו, halalu, so if that wasn't enough
of an excessive amount, now we're going to, you know, exaggerate it
to the nth degree. All of that stuff, all that bread we
just read about was not the bread for the meal, that was
just לעמילן של טבחים, la-amilan shel tabachim, that was just the bread
to put on the pots to draw out the overflow of the
pot. Okay? רב יצחק אמר: Rav Yitzchak amar: הללו לציקי קדירה, halalu
le-tzikei kedeira, all that meat we just discussed, that was just for
some type of like appetizer, that wasn't the main meal, okay, ציקי
קדירה, tzikei kedeira, some type of like I don't know, some minced
meat or something. ואמר רב יצחק: ve-amar Rav Yitzchak: אלף נשים היו
לשלמה, elef nashim hayu li-Shlomo, I'll do you one better, שלמה Shlomo
had a thousand wives, כל אחת ואחת עשתה לו בביתה כך, kol
achas ve-achas asta lo be-veisa kach, each and every one prepared this
meal in her house, so he actually had a thousand times this.
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? זו סבורה שמא אצלי סועד היום, zu sevura
shema etzli so'ed hayom, each one said maybe he'll eat by me
today, וזו סבורה שמא אצלי סועד היום, ve-zu sevura shema etzli so'ed
hayom, he'll eat by me, so each one prepared this meal for
him. Okay, so that was שלמה. Shlomo. ואילו גבי אברהם כתיב, ve-ilu
gabei Avraham ketiv, by אברהם Avraham it's much more modest, it says:
ואל הבקר רץ אברהם ויקח בן בקר רך וטוב, ve-el ha-bakar ratz
Avraham vayikach ben bakar rach va-tov, it sounds like it was only
one cattle. We expand it a little bit, ואמר רב יהודה אמר
רב: ve-amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav: בן בקר, ben bakar, a calf,
אחת, achat, that means one calf, רך, rach, soft, שנים, shenayim, it's
a second cattle, וטוב, va-tov, שלשה. shelosha. Okay, there were three calves.
התם תלתא תורי לתלתא גברי, hasam tlata torei li-tlata gavrei, remember there
were three angels, so each angel got a calf. הכא, hacha, here
although his feast was huge, but it was לכל ישראל ויהודה, le-chol
Yisrael vi-Yehuda, it wasn't just for him, which didn't sound like it
before when the wives were preparing it, it sounded like it was
just for him, but now they're saying it wasn't just for him,
he was feeding the entire Jewish people, שנאמר יהודה וישראל רבים כחול
אשר על השפת הים. she-ne'emar Yehuda vi-Yisrael rabbim ke-chol asher al sefat
ha-yam. Okay, so therefore on a per person basis, okay, it's like
they say, right, lawyers make an enormous amount of money but if
you figure out per hour are they really making minimum wage? So
anyway on a per person basis, okay, so אברהם's Avraham was bigger.
Okay, now: מאי ברבורים אבוסים? mai barburim abusim? What are these stuffed
fowl? אמר רב שאובסים אותם בעל כרחם, amar Rav she-ovsim osam ba'al
korcham, you force feed them, which is exactly how they make, what
is it, foie gras, right, as they force feed these ducks or
something, or again is it geese? Whatever foie gras. Anyway, ושמואל אמר
שאבוסים ועומדים מאליהם, u-Shmuel amar she-abusim ve-omdim me-aleihem, no it means just
that they're naturally fattened. ורבי יצחק אמר: ve-Rabbi Yitzchak amar: מביאים תור
ממרעיה בדלא אניס, mevi'im tor mi-maraya de-la anis, no you bring an
ox from its grazing which has never been like, never been captured,
it's a wild ox, never been put to work, ותרנגולת מאשפה בדלא
אניסה, ve-tarnegoles me-ashpa de-la anisa, and a hen, you know, that's from
its dung heap that has never been put to work to lay
eggs. So basically they're free range, okay, they're free range and therefore
they're fatter, although nowadays the fatter ones are not the free range
ones, but anyway that's what it means. אמר רבי יוחנן: amar Rabbi
Yochanan: מובחר שבבהמה שור, muvchar she-ba-behema shor, the best of all the
animals maybe from a food perspective is the ox, מובחר שבעוף תרנגולת,
muvchar she-ba-of tarnegoles, the best of the animals, of the birds is
the chicken, okay or the hen. אמר אמימר: amar Ameimar: זגא... zaga...
Now Ameimar says here's what it means these fattened fowl: זגסא ואוכמסה
Zagsa ve'uchmasa a fat black hen בי בתניתא, Bei bitnisa, which is
Rashi says בי בתניתא bei bitnisa means I'm trying to remember what
Rashi says, what does Rashi say? Hold on... oh, which is basically
Rashi says fattened in the house or or Rashi says it means
with a big stomach, with a big stomach, דמשתכח ביני אטמי demishtakcha
beini atmi that's found there between its pressing places, it's always eating
on the grate and so on. Okay, another type of a fat
duck דלא מצי פסיע קניא delo matzi pasia canya and it's so
fat that it can't even step over a reed. Okay, so let's
just read one more story about Avraham. ואל הבקר רץ אברהם. Ve'el
habakar ratz Avraham. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Rav בן בקר אחד Ben bakar echad so he said before that's
one. רך שנים Rach shenayim two. טוב שלושה Tov shlosha so three
calves for the three people. ואימא חד Ve'eima chad so why didn't
it, maybe all that means is one calf which is soft and
good. No, כדיאמרי אינשי Kedi'amri inshi people say רכיך וטוב rachich vetov
like soft and good, maybe it's all describing one calf. אי הכי
לכתוב רך טוב Ei hachi lichtov rach tov which says it just
soft good. מאי וטוב Mai vetov why and good? Of course the
grammar demands the vav but anyway שמע מינה לדרשה shma mina ledrasha
it's coming to tell you that it was an extra calf. ואימא
תרי Ve'eima trei so let's say let's say בן בקר רך Ben
bakar rach is one calf, וטוב vetov is a second calf, how
do you know it's three? No, מדטוב לדרשה midetov ledrasha since the
word tov means a separate calf, רך נמי לדרשה rach nami ledrasha
the word rach soft also means it so there were three calves.
Okay, מתיב רבה בר עולא Masiv Rabba bar Ulla or Rabba bar
Ulla asked ואי תימא רב הושעיא ve'isima Rav Hoshaia ואי תימא רב
נתן בר הושעיא ve'isima Rav Nasan bar Hoshaia ויתנהו אל הנער וימהר
לעשות אתו vayitnehu el hana'ar vayimaher la'asot oso he gave it to
the to the lad who went to do it, so it sounds
like it's a single animal that's being prepared. So the Gemara says:
No, כל חד וחד יהיב לנער חד kol chad vechad yeiv lena'ar
chad each animal he gave to a different youth to prepare. So
he gave to the youth to prepare it, but he did that
three times with three separate youths. Okay. Now: ויקח חמאה וחלב ובן
הבקר אשר עשה Vayikach chem'a vechalav uven habakar asher asa he took
the butter and the milk and the calf that he had prepared.
ויתן לפניהם Vayiten lifnehem and he put it in front of them.
דקמא דקמא דמטיא Dekama dekama dematya what does it mean he put
in front of them? As each dish was finished being prepared, אייתי
לקמייהו ayti lekama'ihu he brought it in front of them. It's like
you're at a restaurant, first they bring the first course and then
they remove it and they bring the second right it feels like
an enormous, it's very like, it's sort of like also with Yaakov
and Eisav sending the different like gifts, one comes as soon as
one comes the next one comes afterwards, right it's this feeling of
plenty. Okay, also some people sort of point out that's why he
didn't eat milchig and fleishig together. First they removed the milchig and
then they brought out the fleishig. A little a little retrojecting there
because there's חמאה וחלב chem'a vechalav and then בן הבקר. ben habakar.
Okay ולמה לי תלתא velama li tlata now why did you need
three? Wasn't one calf enough for three people? כי סגי בחד ki
sagi bechad so אמר רב חנא בר רבא Amar Rav Chana bar
Rava כדי להאכילן שלוש לשונות בחרדל kedei le'achilan shalosh leshonos bechardal because
they wanted to give them three tongues in mustard, which was a
delicacy. So they wanted to give it to each person. Of course
a tongue is pretty big, a tongue of an animal, I think
one tongue could've but anyway that's why. Okay, so we'll end here
we'll end with this. So anyway so Avraham's feast in some ways
was bigger, so if you break a promise to Bnei Avraham Yitzchak
v'Yaakov to give them a feast, you're never going to finish feeding
them. All right, to be continued.